Sergey Tulyakov

Snap Inc.
stulyakov@snap.com
sergey.tulyakov@unitn.it

Web GitHub Google Scholar

Summary

Experienced computer vision and machine learning researcher, exploring 2D & 3D computer vision problems, such as face tracking, reconstruction, analysis, and generative modeling for image-to-image translation, video generation, prediction, retargeting. At Snap Research, he was instrumental in developing the technology behind Our Baby: a Snappable that generates a face of a child, given the faces of two potential parents. His inventions enabled multiple real-time neural lenses, including Baby and Gender Swap that became viral. He contributed to snapchat cat, dog, hands tracking technology. Has extensive background in software engineering. He is currently working to help computers understand users and generate pictures, videos, and sounds. His works are published at top computer vision conferences and journals including CVPR, ECCV, ICCV and TPAMI. Before joining Snap Inc., he built the face tracking and reconstruction engine behind http://facify.me app, and authored one of the first video generation works (MoCoGAN). Sergey holds a PhD degree in Information and Communication Technology from the University of Trento, Italy.

Technical skills:

C++, Python, C#, Qt, Boost, CMake, Docker, Kubernetes, GCloud, Shell, Unix, Windows, macOS Scientific computing:

PyTorch, Chainer, scientific python stack, large scale machine learning, Eigen, dlib, OpenCV, PointCloudLibrary(PCL), matlab

Work experience

07/2010 - 09/2012

06/2006 - 06/2010

11/2018 – present	Lead research scientist, Research Lead at SNAP Inc. (Santa Monica, CA, US)
	I am leading the creative vision team focusing on creative applications using machine learning and computer vision techniques.
07/2017 - 11/2018	Senior research scientist at SNAP Inc. (Santa Monica, CA, US)
	Designed and built a system for distributed, reproducible, and accelerated ML training, bringing $60x$ speed-up in ML training job creation and deployment. Currently is the default system for running training of deep models, serving $50+$ active users across the company, with more than $10K$ training jobs run to date.
	Submitted 5 machine learning and computer vision patents.
	Contributed to multiple neural style lenses including OurBaby snappable, young, old face style transforms. Key contributor to the generative neural network distillation technology. Contributed to cat and dog tracking lenses.
01/2017 - 04/2017	Research intern at NVIDIA (Santa Clara, CA, US)
	Worked on motion-content decomposed video generation using Generative Adversarial Networks with Ming-Yu Liu and Jan Kautz.
08/2016 - 11/2016	Research intern at Microsoft Research (Cambridge, UK)
	Together with Sebastian Nowozin and Andrew Fitzgibbon worked on building efficient

Software engineer at Todes, Ltd. (Minsk, Belarus)

hybrids of deep generative and discriminative models, that benefit from using unlabeled

Senior software engineer, project lead at HiQo Solutions, Inc (Minsk, Belarus)

Education

Oct 2012 – Apr 2017	University of Trento (Trento, Italy) PhD in Computer Science. Thesis: A Computer Vision Perspective on Face Analysis: Registration, Tracking, Synthesis
Nov 2014 – Feb 2015	Carnegie Mellon University (Pittsburgh, USA) Research intern at Robotics Institute
Sept 2009 – July 2010	Belarusian State University of Informatics and Radioelectronics (Minsk, Belarus) Master in Computer Science. Final grade: 9 out of 10
Sept 2004 – July 2009	Belarusian State University of Informatics and Radioelectronics (Minsk, Belarus) Bachelor in Computer Science. Diploma with distinction. GPA 8.9. Final grade: 10 out of 10

Selected personal projects

- Facify is a face tracking and 3D face reconstruction technology, enabling real-time face analysis on low-power mobile devices. The technology features a tiny hard drive footprint (20mb) and impressive tracking speed (200 frames per second on iPhone 6)
- FaceCept Face perCept is a technology that allows real-time analysis of people's faces. Key features: gender, age, facial expression, new/returning, attention time recognition. The technology is cross-platform: it runs even in a browser.
- FaceCept3D is a flexible open-source technology for 3D face analysis and recognition, available on GitHub. Key features: head pose, facial expression and action units recognition in real time. FaceCept3D handles head pose ranges much wider than other systems.

Selected scientific projects

- The **ACANTO** project aims at increasing the number of older adults who engage in a regular and sustained physical activity. Developed a real-time method for instantaneous heart rate recognition from face videos.
- The DALi Devices for Assisted Living project aimed at extending autonomous live of elderly
 people beyond home. Developed a real-time system for head pose analysis, tracking and facial expression
 recognition under a wide range of head poses.
- The purpose of the **PerTe Persuasive Technology** project was to aid groups of people in a brainstorming environment. Worked on user monitoring part: track faces, measure attention given/received and analyze speech activity of the subjects.

Professional activities

Events:

- Organising Committee of the 10th Workshop on Human Behaviour Understanding organized in conjuction with ICCV 2019.
- Chair of the first Workshop on 3D Face Alignment in the Wild (3DFAW) & Challenge organized in conjunction with ECCV 2016.

Teaching:

 Graduate course on Teaching Computers to Imagine with Deep Generative Models, University of Trento, Italy. Nov 19-26, 2019 Reviewer:

CVPR 2020, ECCV 2020, ICCV 2019, NeurIPS 2019, ICCV 2017, CVPR 2017, CVPR 2018, CVPR 2019, ECCV 2016, SIGGRAPH ASIA 2018, SIGGRAPH 2019, ICPR 2018

International Journal on Computer Vision IEEE Transactions on Affective Computing

IEEE Transactions on Multimedia

ACM Transactions on Intelligent Systems and Technology

Elsevier Image and Vision Computing

Talks:

- Learning representations for content creation, manipulation and animation, Stanford University, Apr 2020
- Learning representations for video generation, prediction and retargeting, The Fourth Christmas Colloquium on Computer Vision, Skoltech, Moscow, Dec 2018
- Vision-based human understanding, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA, Nov 2018
- Vision-based human understanding at Snap Research, Keynote at ICME Workshop on Faces in Multimedia, San Diego, CA, July 2018
- Computer Vision Perspective on Face Analysis: Registration, Tracking,
 Synthesis, BAIR at UC Berkeley, CA, Mar 2018
- Towards Learning to Imagine Videos with Controlled Content, GTC 2018, San Jose, CA, Apr 2018
- Real-time 3D face tracking using 2D and 3D sensors, Stanford Neuroscience Institute, CA, Apr 2018
- On Disentangling Motion and Content for Video Generation, NIPS Learning Disentangled Representations: from Perception to Control, Los Angeles, CA, 2017
- Head Pose Estimation and Facial Expression Recognition under a Wide Range of Head Poses, Robotics institute, Carnegie Mellon University, PA, Nov 2014

Selected publications

- [1] A. Siarohin, S. Lathuilière, S. Tulyakov, E. Ricci, and N. Sebe. First Order Motion Model for Image Animation. Neural Information Processing Systems, NeurIPS, 2019.
- [2] [Oral] K. Olszewski, S. Tulyakov, O. Woodford, H. Li and L. Luo *Transformable Bottleneck Networks*. International Conference on Computer Vision, ICCV, 2019.
- [3] J. Robinson, Y. Li, N, Zhang, Y. Fu and S. Tulyakov *Laplace landmark localization*. International Conference on Computer Vision, ICCV, 2019.
- [4] [Oral] A. Siarohin, S. Lathuilière, S. Tulyakov, E. Ricci, and N. Sebe. *Animating Arbitrary Objects via Deep Motion Transfer*. Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, CVPR, 2019.
- [5] Z. Geng, C. Cao, S. Tulyakov. 3D Guided Fine-Grained Face Manipulation. Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, CVPR, 2019.
- [6] S. Tulyakov, M.-Y. Liu, X. Yang, and J. Kautz. MoCoGAN: Decomposing Motion and Content for Video Generation. Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, CVPR, 2018.
- [7] W. Wang, S. Tulyakov, N. Sebe. *Recurrent Convolutional Shape Regressions*. Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence, TPAMI, 2018.

- [9] S. Tulyakov, A. Fitzgibbon, and S. Nowozin *Hybrid-VAE: Improving Deep Generative Models using Partial Observations*. Bayesian Deep Learning Workshop, NIPSW, 2017.
- [10] László A. Jeni, Sergey Tulyakov, Lijun Yin, Nicu Sebe, and Jeffrey F. Cohn The First 3D Face Alignment in the Wild (3DFAW) Challenge. European Conference on Computer Vision, ECCV, 2016.
- [11] [Oral] W. Wang, S. Tulyakov, N. Sebe. Recurrent Convolutional Face Alignment. Asian Conference on Computer Vision, ACCV, 2016.
- [12] S. Tulyakov, L. A. Jeni, N. Sebe, and J. Cohn. *Viewpoint-consistent 3D Face Alignment*. Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence, TPAMI.
- [13] [Oral] S. Tulyakov, X. Alameda-Pineda, E. Ricci, L. Yin, N. Sebe, and J. Cohn. Self-Adaptive Matrix Completion for Heart Rate Estimation from Face Videos under Realistic Conditions. Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, CVPR, 2016.
- [14] S. Tulyakov and N. Sebe. Regressing a 3D Face Shape from a Single Image. In International Conference on Computer Vision, ICCV, 2015.
- [15] S. Tulyakov, R. L. Vieriu, E. Sangineto and N. Sebe. FaceCept3D: Real Time 3D Face Tracking and Analysis. In International Conference on Computer Vision Workshops, ICCVW, 2015.
- [16] R. L. Vieriu, S. Tulyakov, E. Sangineto, S. Semeniuta, and N. Sebe. Facial Expression Recognition under a Wide Range of Head Poses. In Face and Gesture Recognition, FG, 2015.
- [17] S. Tulyakov, R. L. Vieriu, S. Semeniuta, and N. Sebe. *Robust Real-Time Extreme Head Pose Estimation*. In International Conference on Pattern Recognition, ICPR, 2014.

Patents

- [1] C. Crutchfield, M. Gusarov, S. Korolev, S. Kotcur, A. Stoliar, S. Tulyakov and A. Wan Generative Neural Network Distillation. USPTO Patent Application.
- [2] C. Cao, Z. Geng, and S. Tulyakov Image Face Manipulation. USPTO Patent Application.
- [3] E. Buehl, J. Hurwitz, S. Vij and S. Tulyakov Cloud Based Machine Learning. USPTO Patent Application.
- [4] S. Tulyakov, M-Y. Liu, X. Yang, and J. Kautz. System and method for content and motion controlled action video generation. Patent Application No: 62/354,475.
- [5] S. Tulyakov, X. Alameda-Pineda, E. Ricci, L. Yin, N. Sebe, and J. Cohn. Self-Adaptive Matrix Completion for Heart Rate Estimation from Face Videos under Realistic Conditions. Patent Application No: 62/480,094.